<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
          "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY app "freedots">
<!ENTITY App "FreeDots">
<!ENTITY bmn "braille music notation">
<!ENTITY Bmn "Braille music notation">
<!ENTITY nimobmn "new international manual of &bmn;">
<!ENTITY omr "optical music recognition">
<!ENTITY XML "<acronym>XML</acronym>">
<!ENTITY email "mlang@delysid.org">

<!ENTITY % unicode-braille
    PUBLIC "-//delYsid//ENTITIES Unicode Braille v1.0//EN"
    "unicode-braille-v10.ent">
%unicode-braille;
]>
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>&App; User Guide</title>

    <productname>&App;</productname>
    <author>
      <firstname>Mario</firstname> <surname>Lang</surname>
      <affiliation>
	<address><email>&email;</email></address>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <copyright>
      <year>2008</year><year>2009</year><year>2010</year>
      <holder role="mailto:&email;">Mario Lang</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>
Permission to use, copy, modify and distribute this document
for any purpose and without fee is hereby granted in perpetuity,
provided that the above copyright notice and this paragraph appear
in all copies.
      </para>
    </legalnotice>

    <releaseinfo>$Id$</releaseinfo>

    <abstract>
      <para>
<application>&App;</application> provides a way for blind individuals to access
scanned sheet music in a convenient format (&bmn;).
      </para>
      <para>
This book serves as an introduction to &bmn; for those readers that are not
familiar with it yet.  It is also the User's Manual for
<application>&App;</application>.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </bookinfo>

  <part><title>Introduction to &bmn;</title>
    <partintro>
      <para>
&Bmn; is an internationally accepted standard for notating music
for visually impaired musicians in a tactile form.
&Bmn; was originally developed by Louis Braille.
      </para>
      <para>
&Bmn; uses the same six-position Braille cell as literary braille.
However braille music assigns an entirely separate meaning to each braille
symbol or group of symbols, different from literary braille, and has its own
syntax and abbreviations.
      </para>
      <para>
Since <application>&App;</application> is mostly useless to a user who can not
read &bmn;, the first part of this book is dedicated to teaching the very
basics of &bmn;.  If you are already familiar with the international &bmn;
standard, you can safely skip over this section.
      </para>
      <para>
Also, german speaking readers might like to refer to the
<ulink url="http://www.braille.ch/musik/">Neues internationales Handbuch der Braillenotenschrift</ulink>
(new international handbook of braille music notation) available from the
internet.
      </para>
    </partintro>

    <chapter><title>Simple monophonic melodies</title>
      <sect1>
	<title>Notes and rests</title>
	<para>
The pitch of the notes are indicated by dots 1, 2, 4, and 5.  The absence or
presence of dots 3 and/or 6 determines the note rhythmic values.  Each note or
rest has two rhythmic value possibilities.
	</para>
	<table>
	  <title>Note and rest symbols</title>
	  <tgroup cols='8'>
	    <thead>
	      <row>
		<entry>Note value</entry>
		<entry>C</entry>
		<entry>D</entry>
		<entry>E</entry>
		<entry>F</entry>
		<entry>G</entry>
		<entry>A</entry>
		<entry>B</entry>
		<entry>rest</entry>
	      </row>
	    </thead>
	    <tbody>
	      <row>
		<entry>wholes or 16ths</entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl13456;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl1356;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl12346;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl123456;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl12356;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl2346;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl23456;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl134;</symbol></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>halves or 32nds</entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl1345;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl135;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl1234;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl12345;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl1235;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl234;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl2345;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl136;</symbol></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>quarters or 64ths</entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl1456;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl156;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl1246;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl12456;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl1256;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl246;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl2456;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl1236;</symbol></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>eighths or 128ths</entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl145;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl15;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl124;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl1245;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl125;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl24;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl245;</symbol></entry>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl1346;</symbol></entry>
	      </row>
	    </tbody>
	  </tgroup>
	</table>
	<para>
For dotted notes, dot 3 represents each print dot following a note.  It is
placed immediately after the braille note.  No other sign comes between the
note and its dot(s).  Dotted rests are treated the same as dotted notes.
	</para>
	<example width="40">
	  <title>Example 1-2 from the &nimobmn;</title>
	  <literallayout class="Monospaced">
	    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
			parse="text" href="example1-2.brl" />
	  </literallayout>
	  <para>
	    <ulink url="example1-2.mid">Listen to this example</ulink>
	  </para>
	</example>
      </sect1>
      <sect1 id="octaveMarks">
	<title>Octave marks</title>
	<para>
Octave marks, rather than clefs on a staff, indicate specific pitch locations
in braille music.  Octaves are numbered from one to seven, beginning with the
lowest C on the normal, seven-octave piano.  Each octave begins on C and
includes all the notes up to, but not including, the next C above.  The fourth
octave begins on the "middle C" of the piano.
	</para>
	<para>
The octave mark is placed immediately before the note to which it applies with
no intervening signs.  The following table shows the octave marks from
1 to 7 placed before quarter-note C.
	</para>
	<table>
	  <title>Octave marks</title>
	  <tgroup cols='2'>
	    <thead><row><entry>Example</entry><entry>Octave name</entry></row></thead>
	    <tbody>
	      <row>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl4;&brl1456;</symbol></entry>
		<entry>contra</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl45;&brl1456;</symbol></entry>
		<entry>great</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl456;&brl1456;</symbol></entry>
		<entry>small</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl5;&brl1456;</symbol></entry>
		<entry>one-lined</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl46;&brl1456;</symbol></entry>
		<entry>two-lined</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl56;&brl1456;</symbol></entry>
		<entry>three-lined</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl6;&brl1456;</symbol></entry>
		<entry>four-lined</entry>
	      </row>
	    </tbody>
	  </tgroup>
	</table>
	<para>
The first note of a piece must be preceded by its octave mark.  For the
succeeding notes the following rules apply:
	</para>
	<orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
if the next note forms an ascending or descending second or third, it does not
receive an octave mark even if it is in a different octave.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
if it forms an ascending or descending fourth or fifth, it only receives an
octave mark if it is in a different octave from the preceding note.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
if it forms a sixth or more, it must always have its own octave mark.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	<para>
These rules are illustrated in the following example from the <quote>Cologne
Key</quote> of 1888.
	</para>
	<example width="40">
	  <title>Example 1-11 from the &nimobmn;</title>
	  <literallayout class="Monospaced">
	    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
			parse="text" href="example1-11.brl"/>
	  </literallayout>
	  <para>
	    <ulink url="example1-11.mid">Listen to this example</ulink>
	  </para>
	</example>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
      <title>Accidentals, key and time signatures</title>
      <sect1>
	<title>Accidentals</title>
        <para>
The following table lists the symbols used to indicate accidentals.
	</para>
	<table><title>Accidentals</title>
	<tgroup cols='2'>
	  <thead><row><entry>Symbol</entry><entry>Description</entry></row></thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row><entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl16;</symbol></entry>
  	         <entry>natural</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row><entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl126;</symbol></entry>
  	         <entry>flat</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row><entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl146;</symbol></entry>
  	         <entry>sharp</entry>
	    </row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
	</table>
	<para>
The sharp, flat and natural signs are placed before the notes,
intervals or other features to which they belong.  They must not be separated
from notes by anything other than <link linkend="octaveMarks">octave marks</link>.
	</para>
	<para>
If an accidental appears above or below a note in print, it is preceded by dot 6
in braille.
	</para>
      </sect1>
      <sect1><title>Key signatures</title>
        <para>
Key signatures reflect the number of flats or sharps, not the actual pitches as
in print.  If there are four or more accidentals in a key signature, the number
sign (dots 3, 4, 5, 6) is used.
	</para>
	<para>
The next note following a key signature must have an octave mark.
If it is not followed by a time signature, it must be followed by a space.
	</para>
      </sect1>
      <sect1><title>Time signatures</title>
      <para>
When time signatures consist of an upper and a lower number in print, the
braille uses upper- and lower-cell numbers with a number sign only at the
beginning of the combination.  An upper-cell number is used for a single-digit
time signature.  In other types of signatures as well, the print is followed
closely.
      </para>
	<table><title>Time signatures</title>
	<tgroup cols='2'>
	  <thead><row><entry>Symbol</entry><entry>Description</entry></row></thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row><entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl46;&brl14;</symbol></entry>
  	         <entry>C or "common" time</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row><entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl456;&brl14;</symbol></entry>
  	         <entry>Barred C or "cut" time</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row><entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl3456;&brl145;&brl256;</symbol></entry>
  	         <entry>4/4</entry>
	    </row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
	</table>
	<para>
A time signature must be followed by a space, and the next note following it
must have an octave mark.
	</para>
	<para>
The key and time signatures are combined with or without one
space between, according to the practice of the nation.
<warning>This is not implemented yet, time and key signatures are combined without a space.</warning>
	</para>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>
    <chapter><title>Contrapuntal lines and chords within a staff</title>
      <para>
Unlike print music notation, braille music is an entirely linear format.
Therefore certain conventions must be used to indicate contrapuntal lines
and chords, situations where more than one note is played simultaneously
within a single staff.
      </para>
      <sect1><title>In-accords</title>
      <para>
Independent contrapuntal lines within a single staff are indicated via
whole-measure or part-measure "in-accords".
      </para>
      </sect1>
      <sect1><title>Interval notation</title>
      <para>
Homophonic chordal sections are written using interval notation.
      </para>
      <table><title>Interval symbols</title>
	<tgroup cols='2'>
	  <thead><row><entry>Symbol</entry><entry>Interval</entry></row></thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row><entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl34;</symbol></entry>
  	         <entry>second</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row><entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl346;</symbol></entry>
  	         <entry>third</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row><entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl3456;</symbol></entry>
  	         <entry>fourth</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row><entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl35;</symbol></entry>
  	         <entry>fifth</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row><entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl356;</symbol></entry>
  	         <entry>sixth</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row><entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl25;</symbol></entry>
  	         <entry>seventh</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row><entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&brl36;</symbol></entry>
  	         <entry>octave</entry>
	    </row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>
  </part>

  <part><title>Obtaining MusicXML scores</title>
    <partintro>
      <para>
&App; is not a full &omr; solution.  To be able to read sheet music, you will
first need to obtain the music you want to read with &App; in MusicXML format.
      </para>
      <para>
The following chapters are concerned with how and where you can obtain sheet
music in MusicXML.
      </para>
    </partintro>

    <chapter><title>What is MusicXML?</title>
      <para>
MusicXML is a &XML; based file format for storing musical notation.  It is
being developed by <ulink url="http://www.recordare.com/">Recordare LLC</ulink>.
      </para>
    </chapter>
    <chapter><title>How to create MusicXML scores?</title>
      <para>
MusicXML is now supported by almost all commercial and a number of free
applications dealing with musical scores in one way or another.
There are basically two ways to obtain a score in MusicXML format.
Either you already have it in some computerized form, then you need
to investigate how to convert your data to MusicXML.  Many commercial
notation editors offer a way to export to MusicXML these days.
If you have the music on paper, you need some &omr; software
to scan and recognize your music and then export to MusicXML.
      </para>
      <para>
A list of applications that allow to save or export to MusicXML
format can be found
<ulink url="http://www.musicxml.org/xml/software.html#NowWrites">on the
recordare website</ulink>.
      </para>
      <sect1><title>Using Sibelius to create MusicXML documents</title>
      <sect2><title>Fingering</title>
	<para>
There are three types of text in Sibelius
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
Staff text: text that applies to a single staff, typically directions for a
single instrument
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	  <para>
System text: text that applies to all staves in the score (though it may
only be displayed above one or two of them), and which will appear in all
parts (if there are any) -- typically tempo or rehearsal directions
	  </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
Blank page text: text that can only be created on a blank page, typically
performance directions or other front matter.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	<para>
If you plan to export your score to MusicXML with <productname> Dolet for Sibelius</productname>
so that you can import it in another music notation program or have Freedots
transcribe your score, Then you not only have to make sure to use the right
text type, but also the right font and style.
	</para>
	<para>
You achieve this by using the word menus, that most Sibelius text edit dialogs
provide.
	</para>
	<para>
An example for fingering:
Open "menu/create/text/other staff text/fingering". Unless you are very
familiar with the text style and font to use, don't just type your fingering
in the edit field, but select a fingering provided in the word menu. You open
this word menu by right clicking with the mouse or by just pressing the
application key.
	</para>
      </sect2>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>
    <chapter><title>MusicXML on the Internet</title>
      <para>
Since MusicXML is increasingly being used as an interchange format between
different music notation software, it is increasingly being used as the
canonical format to distribute musical notation over the Internet.
      </para>
      <para>
Therefore, there is a chance that the music you are looking for is already
available on the Internet in MusicXML format.
      </para>
      <para>
Below is a list of some Internet resources that offer MusicXML files
for download.
      </para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><ulink url="http://www.hausmusik.ch/notenregal/">Hausmusik Notenregal</ulink></term>
	  <listitem><para>A repository of scores in various formats, including MusicXML, from <quote>Verein zur Förderung der Hausmusik</quote> in Switzerland.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><ulink url="http://wikifonia.org/">Wikifonia.Org</ulink></term>
	  <listitem><para>Wikifonia is a collection of Lead Sheets (lyrics, melody and chords) of pop songs.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><ulink url="http://www.pjb.com.au/mus/xml/">Peter J Billam's arrangements of JS Bach for recorder</ulink></term>
	  <listitem><para><personname><firstname>Peter</firstname><othername>J</othername><surname>Billam</surname></personname> provides a few of his <ulink url="http://www.pjb.com.au/mus/">arrangements</ulink> for recorder in MusicXML format for free.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </chapter>
  </part>
  <part><title>Using &App;</title>
    <partintro>
      <para>
Now that we have acquainted ourselves with &bmn; and know how to obtain
MusicXML documents we can go on and examine in
detail how &App; can be used to automatically transcribe scanned sheet music
to &bmn;.
      </para>
    </partintro>
    <chapter><title>Overview</title>
      <para>
The user interface of &App; closely resembles a typical editor application.
At the top is a menu bar for convenient access to the most used actions.
The main part of the application is a text edit window which contains
the result of transcribing the currently opened MusicXML file to &bmn;.
      </para>
      <para>
You can use the caret to navigate inside the resulting braille music
document as in other editing applications.  The caret position is
context sensitive.  For instance, if you move the caret the status
area will automatically be updated with textual information about the braille
symbol currently underneath the caret.
      </para>
      <para>
&App; also offers the possibility to play back the score currently opened.
During playback, the caret position will update synchronous to the music.
Additionally, there is the possibility to play individual parts of a score,
or just a single note.
      </para>
    </chapter>
    <chapter><title>The Menu bar</title>
      <para>This list briefly describes the actions available in the &App;
        menu.</para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><menuchoice>
	    <shortcut>
	      <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>o</keycap></keycombo>
	    </shortcut>
	    <guimenu>File</guimenu>
	    <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem>
	  </menuchoice></term>
	  <listitem><para><action>Open a MusicXML document.</action></para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><menuchoice>
	    <guimenu>File</guimenu>
	    <guimenuitem>Save as...</guimenuitem>
	  </menuchoice></term>
	  <listitem><para><action>Allows saving the currently open file to several file formats.</action></para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<!-- varlistentry>
	  <term><menuchoice>
	    <guimenu>File</guimenu>
	    <guimenuitem>Save as MIDI</guimenuitem>
	  </menuchoice></term>
	  <listitem><para><action>Export the currently opened MusicXML to a standard MIDI file.</action></para></listitem>
	</varlistentry -->
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><menuchoice>
	    <guimenu>File</guimenu>
	    <guimenuitem>Quit</guimenuitem>
	  </menuchoice></term>
	  <listitem><para><action>Exit &App;</action></para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
	    <term><menuchoice>
		<shortcut>
		    <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>f</keycap></keycombo>
		</shortcut>
		   <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
		   <guimenuitem>Fingering</guimenuitem>
	    </menuchoice></term>
	    <listitem><para><action>Allows adding fingering information.</action></para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	
	<varlistentry>
	    <term><menuchoice>
		   <guimenu>Transcription</guimenu>
		   <guimenuitem>Section by Section</guimenuitem>
	    </menuchoice></term>
	    <listitem><para><action>T.b.d.</action></para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	    <term><menuchoice>
		   <guimenu>Transcription</guimenu>
		   <guimenuitem>Bar over Bar</guimenuitem>
	    </menuchoice></term>
	    <listitem><para><action>T.b.d.</action></para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	

	<varlistentry>
	    <term><menuchoice>
		<shortcut>
		    <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>p</keycap></keycombo>
		</shortcut>
		   <guimenu>Playback</guimenu>
		   <guimenuitem>Play/Pause score</guimenuitem>
	    </menuchoice></term>
	    <listitem><para><action>Toggles playing/pause of the currently opened score.</action></para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>



	<varlistentry>
	    <term><menuchoice>
		<shortcut>
		    <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>s</keycap></keycombo>
		</shortcut>
		   <guimenu>Playback</guimenu>
		   <guimenuitem>Stop</guimenuitem>
	    </menuchoice></term>
	    <listitem><para><action>Stops playback of the currently opened score.</action></para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>


	<varlistentry>
	    <term><menuchoice>
		<shortcut>
		    <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>s</keycap></keycombo>
		</shortcut>
		   <guimenu>Playback</guimenu>
		   <guimenuitem>Play on caret move</guimenuitem>
	    </menuchoice></term>
	    <listitem><para><action>If enabled, the note currenty under the cursor is played back upon cursor movement.</action></para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>


	<varlistentry>
	    <term><menuchoice>
		   <guimenu>Playback</guimenu>
		   <guimenuitem>Caret follows playback</guimenuitem>
	    </menuchoice></term>
	    <listitem><para><action>If enabled, the cursor is moved in sync with the actual note playback.</action></para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term><menuchoice>
	    <shortcut>
	      <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>l</keycap></keycombo>
	    </shortcut>
	    <guimenu>Library</guimenu>
	  </menuchoice></term>
	  <listitem><para>For your convenience, &App; ships with a few,
freely distributable scores.  This menu allows you to choose one of the prepackaged scores for transcription and/or playback.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	
	<varlistentry>
	    <term><menuchoice>
	    <shortcut>
	      <keycombo><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo>
	    </shortcut>

	   <guimenu>Help</guimenu>
	   <guimenuitem>Describe Sign</guimenuitem>
	    </menuchoice></term>
	    <listitem><para><action>Displays as textual description of the element currently under the cursor.</action></para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	    <term><menuchoice>
	   <guimenu>Help</guimenu>
	   <guimenuitem>Describe Colors</guimenuitem>
	    </menuchoice></term>
	    <listitem><para><action>Displays as table with all colors used in score syntax highlighting.</action></para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	
	
      </variablelist>
    </chapter>
  </part>
  <appendix><title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
    <qandaset>
      <qandadiv><title>General Information</title>
        <qandaentry>
	    <question id="q-windows"><para>Does &App; work on
	      <productname class="trade"><indexterm zone="q-windows">
	        <primary>Windows</primary></indexterm>Windows</productname>?</para></question>
	    <answer><para>
Yes.  You will need to install <application>Java 1.6</application>.
For proper accessibility support you will also need the
<productname>Java-Access-Bridge</productname> installed.
	    </para></answer>
	  </qandaentry>
	  <qandaentry>
	    <question id="q-linux-brltty"><para>Why can't I read the default output of &App;
	      on <productname class="trade"><indexterm zone="q-linux-brltty">
	           <primary>Linux</primary></indexterm>Linux</productname> with
	      <application><indexterm zone="q-linux-brltty"><primary>BRLTTY</primary></indexterm>BRLTTY</application>?</para></question>
	    <answer><para>&App; uses Unicode by default to output
	      braille and text such that sighted and blind users can read the
	      output without major confusion.</para>
	    <para>However, the Unicode braille row is only supported by the
	      braille display driver BRLTTY on Linux since release 3.10.
	      You will also need the braille fonts provided
	      on <ulink url="http://brl.thefreecats.org/"/>.</para></answer>
	  </qandaentry>
	</qandadiv>
      </qandaset>
  </appendix>
  <appendix><title>Traditional <acronym>UNIX</acronym> manual pages</title>
    <refentry id="freedots">
      <refmeta>
	<refentrytitle>&app;</refentrytitle> <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
	<refmiscinfo class="version">0.6</refmiscinfo>
      </refmeta>

      <refnamediv>
	<refname>&app;</refname>
	<refpurpose>convert MusicXML to &bmn;</refpurpose>
      </refnamediv>

      <refsynopsisdiv>
	<cmdsynopsis>
	  <command>&app;</command>
	  <arg><option>-nw</option></arg>
	  <group>
	    <arg><option>-p</option></arg>
	    <arg><option>--play</option></arg>
	  </group>
	  <group>
	    <arg><option>-w</option> <replaceable>COLUMNS</replaceable></arg>
	    <arg><option>--width</option> <replaceable>COLUMNS</replaceable></arg>
	  </group>
          <group>
            <arg><option>-h</option> <replaceable>LINES</replaceable></arg>
            <arg><option>--height</option> <replaceable>LINES</replaceable></arg>
          </group>
          <arg><option>-mps</option> <replaceable>NUMBER</replaceable></arg>
	  <arg choice="req"><replaceable>MusicXML file</replaceable></arg>
	</cmdsynopsis>
      </refsynopsisdiv>

      <refsect1><title>Description</title>
	<para><application>&App;</application> converts MusicXML files
	  to &bmn;.
	</para>
      </refsect1>
      <refsect1><title>Options</title>
        <para><application>&App;</application> always expects a
	  MusicXML input file on the command line.
	</para>
	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>
	      <option>-nw</option>
	    </term>
	    <listitem><para>
	      Do not start the graphical user interface (batch processing).</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>-p</option></term>
	    <term><option>--play</option></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Play music in addition to converting it to braille.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry id="width">
	    <term><option>-w</option></term>
	    <term><option>--width</option></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	        <indexterm><primary>width</primary><secondary>COLUMNS</secondary></indexterm>
	        Set the desired amount of braille cells used horizontally.</para>
	      <para>The default is 32.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
      </refsect1>
    </refentry>
  </appendix>

  <index/>
</book>

